A Guide to the Virginia Writer's Club Archives, 1951-
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Virginia Writer's Club, 1951-
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 160
2.5 linear feet
Virginia Writer's Club
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Received from Secretary Edgar MacDonald, and separate donations from members.
Historical Information
The Virginia Writer's Club was organized on 20 November 1918 at the instigation of Mr. and Mrs. Samuel Travers Clover and under the sponsorship of Dr. Orie Latham Hatcher, who invited James Branch Cabell and a few other Richmond writers to afternoon tea and proposed the formation of a club "to make Richmond an influence in the world of letters and to line it up with other literary centers of the country".
During its early years the club attracted many who would go on to represent the city and the state in the literary world. Many of its members endorsed the short-lived Reviewer and numerous contributed articles over its four year run. After four years the Club had 45 members, 26 of whom had published books. Other had contributed to magazines, newspapers or other literary-related endeavors Meetings were held monthly and included readings of member's work and an occasional speaker. For much of the period between 1923 and 1961 the Club was led by Hattie Belle Gresham, more of an organizer and promoter of literature than a writer.
In October 1961 the Club was reorganized with new officers and by-laws. The somewhat modified character the Club assumed in 1961 has been maintained ever since. It is an interesting association of published writers in various fields for the promotion of good writing, or, in the words of the by-laws, "to provide a means of exchanging ideas and stimulating the art and craft of professional writing." A history of the Club is included in the collection.
Scope and Content Information
The Club does not possess minutes for the years 1923-1961 and the current collection contains materials from 1951 to 1994. The archives includes correspondence, minutes, manuscripts, achievement notices, news clippings, by-laws, photographs and membership lists. The bulk of the material dates from the 1980s and 1990s and has been submitted to the archives by various members of the club.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arrange alphabetically by topic and chronologically therein.
Organization
Series I in the collection is arranged alphabetically by topic. Series II is composed of material submitted by Gordon and Lois Bennett who served as editors of the club's newsletter.
Contents List
- Series I
  - Achievements of Club Members, n.d. 1978-1987 (Box 1)
    (See also Newspaper Clippings)
  - By-laws, Articles of Incorporation, n.d. 1974-1992 (Box 1)
  - Chapter Areas in Virginia (Box 1)
  - Charlottesville Chapter of the Virginia Writer's Club (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, n.d. 1974-1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Ashe, Arthur, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Baker, Russell 1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Bryan III., Joseph, n.d. 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Clifford, Clark 1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-Haley, Alex 1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-MacDonald, Edgar, n.d. 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-Styron, William 1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-Whitney, Phyllis A. 1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-Wolfe, Tom 1972-1990 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-President 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Ellen Glasgow Festival-Promotional materials, Misc. (Box 2)
  - History, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Infonet (Box 2)
  - Manuscript- Mind Full of Place by Anne Hobson Freeman, lecture at VWC meeting 2/1/86 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript- Hunter Stagg: Over There in Paris with Gertrude Stein by Edgar MacDonald (Box 2)
  - Manuscript-J ames Branc Cabell Edgar MacDonald, lecture at The Women's Club 1/25/67 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript- Speaking of the Brontes by Melvin M. Scott, lecture given a VWC meeting 5/1/69 (Box 2)
  - Meeting Announcements, n.d. 1971-1992 (Box 2)
  - Membership Committee, n.d. 1973-1992 (Box 2)
  - Member Qualifications and Structure Committee 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Membership Roster, n.d. 1977-1985 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, Reports, n.d. 1973-1994 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Newsletter 1978 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter announcements (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings (Virginia Writer's Club, members, speakers), n.d. 1951-1991 (Box 3)
  - News Releases (Box 3)
  - Officers, Committee Member Lists (Box 3)
  - Photograph-Astley, Thea and VWC Reception 1990 (Box 3)
  - Program Support Committee (Box 4)
  - Speaker's Committee (Box 4)
  - Statewide Activities 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Traveler Chapter (Box 4)
  - Treasurer 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Writers Club Yearbook 1988-1994, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Whaley, John-Miscellaneous Correspondence, Notes, Committee Material 1994-1996 (Box 4)
  - Workshop 1995 (Box 4)
  - Workshop-Correspondence 1995 (Box 4)
  - Young Writers Club (Box 4)
- Series II
  - Achievement Notices (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, n.d. 1990-1993 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (1 of 3) 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (2 of 3) 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (3 of 3) 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1993 (Box 5)
  - Fee Dues-Correspondence 1992 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Publications (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, James Doherty Collected Materials 1983-1989 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Minutes, Reports, n.d. 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper/Journal Clippings, n.d. (1 of 3) 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper/Journal Clippings, n.d. (2 of 3) 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper/Journal Clippings, n.d. (3 of 3) 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Newsletter, n.d. 1991 (Box 7)
  - Newsletter 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Virginia Writers' Club-Application for Membership; Benefit of Affiliation statement, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow Festival Poster, oversized (Oversize Drawer #25)
  - Certificate of Recognition from Gov. Wilder/Photo, oversized (Oversize Drawer # 25)